Michael K. Mabey



Albuquerque, NM

(480) 788-3411 ♦ mmabey@asu.edu & mikemabey.com &

EDUCATION

PhD Computer Science — Information Assurance (expected) May 2017 Arizona State University Tempe, AZ

Research Topics: Email forensics, Chrome OS forensics, Collaborative forensics

M.S. Computer Science - Information Assurance Aug 2011 Arizona State University Tempe, AZ

Committee: Gail-Joon Ahn (Chair), Stephen S. Yau, Dijiang Huang

In order to catch the smartest criminals in the world, digital forensic examiners need a means of collaborating and sharing information that is not prohibitively difficult to use and that complies with standard operating procedures and the rules of evidence. In this work I present the design and implementation of the Collaborative Forensic Framework (CUFF) which is a cloud-based forensic analysis environment that facilitates collaboration among examiners and their trusted colleagues. CUFF makes a positive impact on forensic examiners' efficiency by helping them leverage their network of subject matter experts while also tapping into the scalability and power of the cloud.

B.S. Computer Science — Information Systems

May 2009 **Utah State University** Logan, UT

Sandia National Laboratories

EXPERIENCE SUMMARY	
Research Assistant Security Engineering for Future Computing (SEFCOM) Lab	Nov 2009 – Present o∉, ASU Tempe, AZ
Teaching Assistant Arizona State University	<i>Aug 2010 – Dec 2015</i> Tempe, AZ
SAT/ACT Instructor Minerva Learning, LLC	Sep 2015 – Oct 2015 Chandler, AZ
Summer Intern Arizona Cyber Threat Response Alliance (ACTRA)	<i>Jul 2015 – Sep 2015</i> Phoenix, AZ
Teaching Assistant (Instructor of Record) Arizona State University	<i>Aug 2011 – Dec 2014</i> Tempe, AZ
Student Trainee (Civilian) US Army	Jun 2013 – Aug 2013, Jun 2014 – Aug 2014 Fort Meade, MD
Graduate Student Summer Intern	May 2011 – Jul 2011

Graduate Student Recruitment Specialist/Webmaster Jul 2006 - Aug 2009 Electrical & Computer Engineering Department USU Logan, UT

Revised 04/25/2016 1 Mabey

HONORS AND AWARDS

· DoD Information Assurance Scholarship Program (IASP) Recipient (4 years)

2012 - 2016

· Inducted into Eta Kappa Nu (HKN) Engineering Honors Society

Nov 2010

· Eagle Scout, Boy Scouts of America

2002

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Digital Forensics

Web and Email Forensics

Forensics on Non-Traditional Devices

· Cyber Security

Threat Intelligence Sharing

Web Security

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant

Nov 2009 - Present

Security Engineering for Future Computing (SEFCOM) Lab &, ASU Lab Directors: Gail-Joon Ahn, Adam Doupé

Tempe, AZ

· Projects:

• Researched forensic techniques for Chrome OS/Chromium OS by creating tools in Python and using libvirt to interface with a KVM/QEMU hypervisor. (In progress)

Publications: [S1], [P1], [T1], [T2]

• Developed a web email forensic acquisition approach that reestablishes persistent cookie sessions stored by a browser, and automated the process using Python and Selenium.

Publications: [C1]

· Designed and implemented the core components of a modular, highly scalable, collaboration-centric digital forensic framework built on the OpenStack cloud architecture. Functions of the components included distributed job scheduling, storage management, and concise evidence representation and transmission.

Publications: [C3], [J2], [P3]

Sponsors

 Department of Defense Information Assurance
 Department of Energy Scholarship Program (IASP)

National Science Foundation

PUBLICATIONS

Peer-Reviewed Conference Proceedings

- [C1] Justin Paglierani, Mike Mabey, and Gail-Joon Ahn. "Towards Comprehensive and Collaborative Forensics on Email Evidence". In: Collaborative Computing: Networking, Applications and Worksharing (Collaboratecom), 2013 9th International Conference Conference on. October 2013, pp. 11–20. DOI: 10.4108/icst.collaboratecom.2013.254125 &.
- [C2] Wonkyu Han, Mike Mabey, and Gail-Joon Ahn. "Simulation-Based Validation for Smart Grid Environments". In: Information Reuse and Integration (IRI), 2013 IEEE 14th International Conference on. August 2013, pp. 14-21. DOI: 10.1109/IRI.2013.6642448 c.
- [C3] Mike Mabey and Gail-Joon Ahn. "Towards Collaborative Forensics: Preliminary Framework". In: Information Reuse and Integration (IRI), 2011 IEEE International Conference on. August 2011, pp. 94-99. DOI: 10.1109/IRI.2011.6009527 R.

Peer-Reviewed Book Chapters & Journal Papers

- [J1] Wonkyu Han, **Mike Mabey**, Gail-Joon Ahn, and Tae Sung Kim. "Simulation-Based Validation for Smart Grid Environments: Framework and Experimental Results". In: *Integration of Reusable Systems*. Ed. by Thouraya Bouabana-Tebibel and Stuart H. Rubin. Vol. 263. Advances in Intelligent Systems and Computing. Springer International Publishing, 2014, pp. 27–44. ISBN: 978-3-319-04716-4. DOI: 10.1007/978-3-319-04717-1_2&.
- [J2] **Mike Mabey** and Gail-Joon Ahn. "Towards Collaborative Forensics". In: *Information Reuse and Integration in Academia and Industry*. Ed. by Tansel Özyer, Keivan Kianmehr, Mehmet Tan, and Jia Zeng. Springer Vienna, 2013, pp. 237–260. ISBN: 978-3-7091-1537-4. DOI: 10.1007/978-3-7091-1538-1_12 \array.

Poster Presentations

- [P1] **Mike Mabey**, Jeremy Whitaker, Gail-Joon Ahn, and Adam Doupé. *Towards Forensics for Web Thin Clients. Symposium on Information Assurance Research and Education, ASU.* November 2015.
- [P2] Jeremy Whitaker, **Mike Mabey**, Gail-Joon Ahn, and Adam Doupé. *Forensic Analysis on Mobile Devices*. *Symposium on Information Assurance Research and Education, ASU*. October 2014.
- [P3] **Mike Mabey**, Justin Paglierani, and Gail-Joon Ahn. *Towards Collaborative Forensics. Workshop on Information Assurance Research and Education, ASU*. April 2012.

Works Submitted (In Press)

[S1] **Mike Mabey**, Adam Doupé, Ziming Zhao, and Gail-Joon Ahn. "dbling: Identifying Extensions Installed on Encrypted Web Thin Clients". In: *Digital Investigation* (2016). The Proceedings of the Sixteenth Annual DFRWS Conference (In Press).

TEACHING INTERESTS

- · Computer and Network Forensics
- · Advanced Topics in Digital Forensics
- · Information Assurance

- · Security Toolkit Programming with Python
- Cryptography
- Software Security

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant

Arizona State University

Aug 2010 - Dec 2015

Tempe, AZ

- · CSE 465 Information Assurance with Dr. Gail-Joon Ahn: Fall 2010, Fall 2015.
- \cdot CSE 469 Computer and Network Forensics with Dr. Gail-Joon Ahn: Spring 2015.
- FSE 100 Introduction to Engineering with Dr. Ryan Meuth: Spring 2014.
- · CSE 423/424 Capstone I and CSE 485/486 Capstone II with Dr. Debra Calliss: Spring 2014.
- · CSE 467 Data & Information Security with Dr. Gail-Joon Ahn: Spring 2011.

SAT/ACT Instructor Minerva Learning, LLC Sep 2015 - Oct 2015

Chandler, AZ

· Individual tutor for a high school student preparing for the PSAT.

Teaching Assistant (Instructor of Record)

Aug 2011 - Dec 2014

Arizona State University

Tempe, AZ

- · CSE 465 Information Assurance: Fall 2014.
- · FSE 100 Introduction to Engineering: Fall 2011 Fall 2013 (5 semesters).

Mabey Revised 04/25/2016 3

TECHNICAL STRENGTHS & QUALIFICATIONS

Programming Languages Python, C/C++, HTML, CSS, LATEX

Forensic Tools FTK, Sleuth Kit & Autopsy, dd, HxD, etc.

Protocols & APIs JSON, XML, REST, STIX/TAXII

Network Administration/Security OpenVPN, Wireshark, ufw, Apache, lighttpd

Windows, Linux, Chrome OS Operating Systems

Databases MySQL, SQLite

SERVICE

Department

2009, 2010, 2014, 2015 Team Leader: ASU team in the UCSB International CTF

· Panelist: PhD Open House Student Panel Feb 2014, Feb 2015

Profession

· Student Program Committee Member:

 IEEE Security & Privacy 2016

· Conference Proceedings Subreviewer:

2013, 2014, 2015, 2016 ACM CODASPY

SACMAT 2014

 ASIACCS 2014

· Student Volunteer:

 ACM CCS 2014

Technical Blog Posts

- [T1] Mike Mabey. How to check out an old version of Chromium OS. http://mikemabey.blogspot.com/ 2016/02/how-to-check-out-old-version-of.html &. February 26, 2016.
- [T2] Mike Mabey. Fixing repo init to check out Chromium OS code. http://mikemabey.blogspot.com/2015/ 01/fixing-repo-init-to-check-out-chromium.html &. January 30, 2015.
- [T3] Mike Mabey. Getting into Developer Mode on the HP Pavilion 14 Chromebook. http://mikemabey. blogspot.com/2013/05/getting-into-developer-mode-on-hp.html ♂. May 8, 2013.
- [T4] Mike Mabey. OpenVPN Update: Fixed! http://mikemabey.blogspot.com/2012/06/openvpn-updatefixed.html &. June 6, 2012.
- [T5] **Mike Mabey**. Debian on Android and my quest for a full-fledged terminal Python IDE. http://mikemabey. blogspot.com/2012/06/debian-on-android-and-my-quest-for-full.html &. June 23, 2012.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Summer Intern *Jul 2015 – Sep 2015* Phoenix, AZ

Arizona Cyber Threat Response Alliance (ACTRA)

· Designed an operationalized workflow for AZ Infragard member organizations to share threat intelli**gence** through a common **STIX/TAXII** platform.

Student Trainee (Civilian)

US Army

Jun 2013 - Aug 2013, Jun 2014 - Aug 2014 Fort Meade, MD

· Summer internships in connection with DoD IASP scholarship.

Revised 04/25/2016 Mabey 4

Graduate Student Summer Intern

Sandia National Laboratories

May 2011 – Jul 2011 Albuquerque, NM

- Helped design a dynamic malware analysis framework built on OpenStack, allowing incident responders to define customizable analysis environments and use arbitrary analysis tools in triage or manual analysis mode.
- · Wrote **Python** scripts to automate the setup process for using a SheevaPlug computer as a wireless intrusion detection agent running **Kismet**.

Graduate Student Recruitment Specialist/Webmaster

Jul 2006 – Aug 2009

Electrical & Computer Engineering Department USU

Logan, UT

- Primary responsibilities included maintaining and augmenting the department website using PHP, MySQL, and other basic web technologies like CSS, JavaScript, and an SMTP server.
- · Completed multiple graphics design projects for the department using **Photoshop**, **Illustrator**, and **GIMP**.

PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

· IEEE (Student Member)

· IEEE Computer Society

PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

· Preparing Future Faculty (GRD 791 at ASU)

Aug 2015 - Present

The Preparing Future Faculty (PFF) program is a year-long series of seminars, discussions and activities designed to expose graduate students and postdocs more fully to the realities of teaching, research and service in higher education.

· Writing Effectively: The Art of Argument (Workshop at ASU)

Oct 2015

REFERENCES

Please feel free to contact any of my references.

Gail-Joon Ahn

Professor of Computer Science and Engineering

Fulton Entrepreneurial Professor

School of Computing, Informatics and Decision Systems Engineering

Ira A. Fulton Schools of Engineering, Arizona State University

Brickyard Engineering (BYENG) Bldg, Room 486

699 S. Mill Avenue Tempe, AZ 85281

Phone: (480) 965-9007 Fax: (480) 965-2751

http://www.public.asu.edu/~gahn1/&

gahn@asu.edu@

Adam Doupé

Assistant Professor of Computer Science and Engineering School of Computing, Informatics and Decision Systems Engineering Ira A. Fulton Schools of Engineering, Arizona State University Brickyard Engineering (BYENG) Bldg, Room 472 699 S. Mill Avenue

Tempe, AZ 85281 Fax: (480) 965-2751 http://adamdoupe.com&doupe@asu.edu&

Frank J. Grimmelmann

President & CEO/Intelligence Liaison Officer Arizona Cyber Threat Response Alliance (ACTRA)

Phone: (623) 551-1526 Fax: (623) 551-4221

fgrimmelmann@actraaz.org &

Stephen S. Yau

Director, Information Assurance Center Professor of Computer Science and Engineering School of Computing, Informatics and Decision Systems Engineering Ira A. Fulton Schools of Engineering, Arizona State University Brickyard Engineering (BYENG) Bldg, Room 488 699 S. Mill Avenue

Tempe, AZ 85281 Phone: (480) 965-2647 Fax: (480) 965-2751

http://dpse.eas.asu.edu/yau/♂

yau@asu.edu ♂